Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
本系列内容基于并受到锡吕·玛塔吉·涅玛拉·德维 (Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi) 教诲的启发，
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
旨在探索两个相互关联的领域之间 的进化关系，
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
这两个领域在物质和精微层面 表达了人类的意识。
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
本系列将阐明关于当前科学对神经解剖学 （特别是自主神经系统）的理解，
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
与传统瑜伽文献中描述的
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
“精微能量系统” 之间的复杂相互作用。
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最后本系列将带领观众 踏上探索之旅，
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
藉由锡吕·玛塔吉所教导的冥想法， 去体验这些关系。
Today, we are diving into the fascinating intersection
今天，我们将深入探讨 神经科学与灵性之间
of neuroscience and spirituality,
的精彩交汇点，
exploring how the human nervous system, the autonomic nervous system,
探索人类神经系统、 自主神经系统、
and the brain's unique organization relate to our spiritual experiences.
大脑独特的组织结构等 如何与我们的灵性体验相关联。
Join us as we unravel the mysteries of consciousness,
让我们一同来揭开意识的奥秘、
evolution's role in shaping the brain,
了解进化在塑造大脑过程中扮演的角色，
and the profound insights from ancient texts like the Bhagavad Gita.
以及如《薄伽梵歌》等古代典籍中 蕴含的深刻洞见。
Did you ever wonder how our brains perceive spirituality?
您是否曾想过 我们的大脑是如何感知灵性的？
Or how ancient texts might align with modern neuroscience?
或者古代典籍如何与 现代神经科学相契合？
Get ready for a mind-expanding conversation that will challenge your understanding
让我们开始一场拓展思维的对话吧！ 它将挑战您
of the human experience.
对人类经验的理解。
Let's start to uncover these and more intriguing questions with Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
让我们与阿希什·普拉丹博士一起 开始揭示这些以及更多有趣的问题。
Dr. Pradhan is a distinguished medical leader who has led cutting-edge work
普拉丹博士是一位杰出的医学领导者， 他在神经病学和心血管医学领域
in neurology and cardiovascular medicine.
领导了前沿性的工作。
And his career is a testament to strategic leadership
他的卓越职业生涯证明了 他的战略领导能力，
and a deep commitment to patient-centric care.
以及对以患者为中心的护理的坚定承诺。
With a distinguished career spanning pivotal roles
他辉煌的职业生涯中担任过多个关键角色，
in drug development at multiple global pharma R&amp;D organizations,
例如在多家全球制药研发机构 从事药物开发工作，
Dr. Pradhan has pioneered groundbreaking initiatives
普拉丹博士开创了 多项突破性举措，
that redefine patient care and medical strategy.
为患者护理和医疗策略重新定义。
And throughout his career, Dr. Pradhan has led
在他的整个职业生涯中， 普拉丹博士领导了
even greater innovative initiatives
更多创新的举措，
that bridge scientific advancements with holistic patient care,
将科学进步与 整体患者护理相结合，
earning him accolades for his pragmatic approach and global impact.
他务实的方法和全球影响力 为他赢得了赞誉。
And in addition to this professional excellence, he is a longstanding meditation practitioner,
除了事业有卓越成就， 他也是一位长期的冥想练习者、
coach, and mentor.
教练与导师。
Ashish was introduced to Sahaja Yoga as a meditation practice
阿希什在印度孟买很小的时候 就接触了霎哈嘉瑜伽，
at a very young age in Mumbai, India.
这种冥想练习。
And having experienced its profound benefits, both personally and professionally,
在亲身体验了其在个人和专业上带来的深远益处后，
Ashish has been a passionate advocate as well as an instructor
阿希什一直是霎哈嘉冥想法的热衷倡导者
of the Sahaja meditation technique.
和指导老师。
Over the past decades, he has led seminars and workshops for introducing this meditation
在过去几十年里，他曾在多个国家 举办过研讨会和讲座，
in multiple countries.
向大众介绍这种冥想法。
And the experiences he has gleaned through these years of global interactivity
多年来，通过这些全球性的互动， 他积累了丰富的经验，
have allowed him time to reflect on how best to introduce this meditation
这让他有时间反思 如何最好地将这种冥想
to culturally-diverse audiences through the unifying language
通过现代科学这一 共通的语言，
of modern science.
介绍给不同文化背景的观众。
Welcome, Dr. Ashish, and it's such a pleasure to have you join us.
欢迎您，阿希什博士，非常荣幸 能邀请您加入我们。
Thank you, Monikaji. Thanks for having me.
谢谢你，莫尼卡。 感谢你的邀请。
Let's start by talking to our audiences a little bit about your meditation journey
让我们先和观众们聊一聊 您的冥想之旅
and the founder of this meditation.
以及这位冥想法的创始人吧。
Sahaja was established by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi
霎哈嘉是由锡吕·玛塔吉·涅玛拉·德维 在印度创立的，
as Sahaja Yoga in India.
被称为霎哈嘉瑜伽。
It's also recognized as Sahaja Yoga Meditation or Sahaja Meditation around the world
它在全球也被称为 霎哈嘉瑜伽冥想或霎哈嘉冥想，
in 1970 in India.
于1970年在印度创立。
And it is a very simple, straightforward meditation technique
这是一种非常简单、 直接的冥想技巧，
which, at its very core relies or is defined by the awakening
其核心在于唤醒一种 潜藏于我们每个人内在的
of a dormant energy that lies within each one of us
沉睡的能量， 这种能量位于
in the sacrum bone.
我们的骶骨中。
And as we go into this series, we will talk a lot about
随着我们深入这个系列， 我们将谈论很多关于
how the whole anatomical features relate to spirituality.
整个解剖学特点 如何与灵性相关联。
But the awakening of this energy and its ascent through the energy centers
然而，这种能量的唤醒 以及它穿越其上方的能量中心
that lie above it, and its ultimate manifestation through the seventh energy center by piercing it,
并最终穿透第七个能量中心 而显现出来，
so-called in spiritual terms, is what meditation is truly about.
用灵性术语来说， 这才是真正的冥想。
But in fact, beyond that, it's what is called a yogic state.
但实际上，除此之外， 它更是一种被称为“瑜伽状态”的境界。
So, this was something that Shri Mataji started in 1970.
这是锡吕·玛塔吉在1970年开始的。
It is now practiced in over 110-120 countries around the world.
现在，全球有超过 110到120个国家的人在练习它。
At a very young age, my father took to this form of meditation practice,
我很小的时候，我的父亲 开始接触这种冥想练习，
and that's how I took to it as well.
我也是这样开始练习的。
And I was pretty young, about ten years old.
那时我相当年轻， 大约十岁。
And thereafter, I have been a regular practitioner of this form of meditation.
从那以后，我就一直是 这种冥想的常规练习者。
So, Dr. Pradhan, before we embark on exploring the spiritual aspects of being human,
普拉丹博士，在我们开始探索 作为人的灵性层面之前，
why is it crucial to first understand the complexities of our nervous system?
为什么首先理解我们神经系统的 复杂性是至关重要？
And how does this understanding lay a foundation for our spiritual journey?
这种理解又如何为我们的 灵性之旅奠定基础呢？
Excellent questions. So, the journey begins
非常好的问题。 所以，旅程的起点
with what it means to be human.
是“何以为人”。
So, when we say we are human beings, that is, we are Homo sapiens,
所以，当我们说我们是人类， 也就是智人（Homo sapiens），
we are defined by a set of biological characteristics,
我们是由一系列 生物学特征来定义的，
a set of genomic characteristics,
一系列基因组特征，
the way the genetic code defines us as humans.
也就是基因编码 将我们定义为人类的方式。
So, for example, as everybody knows now in the twenty-first century,
比如，现在21世纪的 每个人都知道，
we have 46 chromosomes within us.
我们体内有46条染色体。
So, those are both autosomes as well as sex chromosomes.
这些染色体包括常染色体 和性染色体。
And that is what makes us human.
这就是我们之所以为人的原因。
The human genome project unraveled the entire genetic sequence.
人类基因组计划 揭示了完整的基因序列。
Meaning, the chemistry of it could be written out.
也就是说，它的化学构成可以被写出来。
And if you read that, it can also be seen as just a set of alphabets
如果你去读它，它也可以被看作 只是一套字母表，
of about six billion base pairs of how the genetic code is written.
大约有60亿个碱基对 构成了我们的基因编码。
But that could be done for every living organism that exists on the planet.
但是，地球上存在的每一个生物 都可以做到这一点。
So, we have a particular genetic code that is unique to us.
我们有一个特定的基因编码， 对我们来说是独一无二的。
Does that make us human?
这是否就让我们成为人类了呢？
So, what makes us human is not the common chemistry that binds us;
所以，让我们成为人类的，并非那将我们 联系在一起的共同化学物质；
it's the same as in jellyfish, it's the same as in fish,
它和水母中的一样， 和鱼类中的一样，
it's the same as in mammals, in vertebrates, in reptiles.
和哺乳动物、脊椎动物、 爬行动物中的都一样。
Every living organism has a genetic code. Does that make them human?
每个生物都有一个基因编码。 这是否就让它们成为人类了呢？
Well, what makes us human is a very unique capacity
嗯，让我们成为人类的 是一种非常独特的能力，
that, so far at least, we believe is very unique to us
至少到目前为止，我们相信 这对我们这个物种来说是
as a species.
非常独特的。
And that is the ability to differentiate between what is self and non-self.
那就是区分 “自我”与“非我”的能力。
And that defines us as a human being.
这定义了我们作为人类的存在。
It intersects science, philosophy, and religion.
它与科学、哲学和宗教 相互交织。
It is at this crucial intersection where we begin to define ourselves as humans.
正是在这个关键的交汇点， 我们开始将自己定义为人类。
And therefore, at the very outset, as we begin this journey,
因此，在我们开始这段旅程之初，
it is imperative that we realize, that we recognize, what it means to be human.
我们必须意识到、认识到 何以为人。
And within that construct of what it means to be human
在“何以为人”的这个 概念框架内，
is this, somewhere within us, almost a hard-wired system
我们内在的某个地方， 几乎像一个硬连线系统，
that allows us to be able to differentiate between us as me, for example, I,
让我们能够区分 “我们”与”我“，比如“我”，
the sense of I-ness versus non-I-ness.
这种“我”的感觉，与“非我”的感觉。
Every human being says, "This is my body, this is my person, this is me."
每个人都会说：“这是我的身体， 这是我这个人，这是我。”
So, who is this "me"? What gives a human being the awareness
那么，这个“我”是谁呢？ 是什么赋予了人类这种意识，
to say, "This is I," versus somebody else?
去说“这是我”，而不是其他人？
Do elephants do it? Do lions do it? Do tigers do it? Do salmon fish do it?
大象会这么做吗？狮子会吗？ 老虎会吗？三文鱼会吗？
Does a condor flying in the air do it?
在空中飞翔的秃鹰会吗？
We, so far, do not know, but it is assumed, based on a number of experiments
到目前为止，我们还不知道， 但根据一系列已进行的实验，
that have been conducted, that the closest it comes to
我们推测，最接近这种能力的
are the great apes, the orangutans, the chimpanzees,
是大型猿类，如猩猩、 黑猩猩，
who can have this understanding between self and non-self.
它们能够理解 自我与非我之间的区别。
And that, in essence, is the critical starting point to understand human spirituality and its origins.
而这，本质上，是理解人类灵性 及其起源的关键起点。
So, Dr. Pradhan, evolution has sculpted our brains over the millennia,
那么，普拉丹博士，进化 在千百万年间塑造了我们的大脑，
something that you were already just touching upon.
这也是您刚才 刚刚触及到的话题。
Could you paint a vivid picture of this evolutionary journey,
您能为我们生动地描绘一下 这段进化的旅程吗？
highlighting any fascinating adaptations that have shaped our brain structure and function
重点介绍那些塑造了我们大脑结构 和功能的迷人适应性变化，
into the marvel that it is today?
使其成为今天这样的奇迹？
I am going to expand on that question,
我将扩展这个问题，
take a little bit of time to explain. It is a critical question.
花一点时间来解释。 这是一个关键问题。
So, let us start off at the very beginning.
那么，让我们从最远古开始说起。
So, life as we know originated as single-cellular organisms in water.
我们所知的生命起源于 水中的单细胞生物。
As the planet was formed after the Big Bang,
在宇宙大爆炸后， 地球形成，
it started cooling, the gases cooled down, the crust was formed, the oceans were formed,
它开始冷却，气体冷却， 地壳形成，海洋形成，
the elements came together,
各种元素汇集在一起，
and as the planet cooled down, at some point in time,
随着地球冷却， 在某个时间点，
this unique chemistry came together of carbon-based elements
这种独特的化学物质， 即碳基元素，聚集在一起，
and formed what we call life.
形成了我们所说的生命。
So, it started off as unicellular organisms that, over billions of years, matured,
生命始于单细胞生物， 经过数十亿年的成熟演化，
grew first into plankton, then small fish, then bigger fish.
先是变成了浮游生物， 然后是小鱼，再到大鱼。
Gradually, they came up on land, became amphibians;
渐渐地，它们登上陆地， 变成了两栖动物；
then we had one of them: reptiles.
然后我们有了其中一类：爬行动物，
Mammals are a subgroup of vertebrates characterised by a spine
从爬行动物我们有了 脊椎动物和无脊椎动物；
that is, one with the vertebral column: mammals,
即有脊柱的一类：哺乳动物，
and then, of course, us, as part of the mammalian species.
然后，当然，就是作为 哺乳动物物种一部分的我们。
If we take a look at some of the most primitive life forms,
如果我们看一下 一些最原始的生命形式，
what they exactly are is a single cell or a multicellular organism
它们确切地说就是一个单细胞 或多细胞生物，
that indulges in the most basic of functions.
从事着最基本的功能。
It eats, it consumes nutrients, it somehow survives, it reproduces,
它进食，消耗营养， 以某种方式生存，繁殖，
and comes to an end at some point in time,
然后在某个时间点 走向终结，
and the cycle repeats itself.
然后循环往复。
So, if you look at the structure of these organisms,
所以，如果你观察 这些生物的结构，
what we see are rudiments
我们会看到一些雏形，
of what we call the nervous system.
也就是我们所说的神经系统。
The nervous system is a system
神经系统是一个
that allows electrophysiological currents to be generated.
能够产生电生理电流的系统。
If you think of what a nervous system is, think of it as electric currents
如果你思考什么是神经系统， 可以把它想象成产生的电流，
that are generated. These are voltage changes that happen
这些是发生在细胞膜两侧的
across cell membranes.
电压变化。
So, like, if you take a voltmeter and put it across,
所以，就像你拿一个 电压表放在两端，
you can see the changes that happen across a membrane,
你就能看到膜两侧发生的 变化，
and it is called a transmembrane potential.
这被称为跨膜电位。
So, why is this important? It seems to go a little deeper
那么，为什么这很重要呢？ 这似乎比你问的问题
into the question you are asking, but this is important,
要更深入一些，但这很重要，
because life, literally, is electricity.
因为生命，从字面上说，就是电。
Life, literally, is defined by the presence of an electric charge.
生命，从字面上说，是由 电荷的存在来定义的。
So, for example, (and I will get back to the question you are answering),
所以，例如，（我会回到 你正在回答的问题），
but this is again important.
但这同样很重要。
For example, when life comes to an end, even particularly in human beings,
例如，当生命走到尽头时， 尤其是在人类身上，
we say it is not just when the heart stops, but it is when the brain stops.
我们说，这不仅仅是心脏停止跳动， 而是大脑停止运作。
It is called brain death.
这被称为脑死亡。
So, when that electrical activity that exists,
所以，当那种存在的电活动，
not just within the heart that causes the heart to pump,
不仅仅是使心脏泵血的 心脏电活动，
but also the brain waves, they come to an end.
也包括脑电波， 当它们都停止时。
And the reason these brain waves are actually formed
而这些脑电波 之所以能够形成，
is because of the movement of sodium and potassium
是因为钠和钾 在细胞膜两侧的
across membranes.
移动。
So, back to what we're discussing. If you look at the most primitive forms of life,
所以，回到我们讨论的话题。 如果你观察最原始的生命形式，
they do not have a well-developed nervous system.
它们并没有 发育完善的神经系统。
They just seem to have these minor, sort of, threads of electrical impulses
它们似乎只有这些微弱的、 类似于电脉冲的线索，
that are just like a small network that keeps on popping up.
就像一个小网络一样 不断地涌现。
And that is how we say the cell is alive.
这就是我们说细胞是活的 原因。
Fast forward, what we see, if you take a look at the phylogenetic nature,
快进一下，我们所看到的， 如果你观察物种的系统发育，
if you go from fish to reptile to basic mammal to, say, man.
如果你从鱼类到爬行动物 到基本哺乳动物，再到人类。
For example, you take a fish, you take a serpent,
例如，你拿一条鱼， 一条蛇，
you take a mouse, and then a human brain, what we find is that the basic requirements
一只老鼠，然后是一个人脑， 我们会发现，维持植物性功能——
for maintaining vegetative functions - breathing, locomotion - that is, movement,
呼吸、运动——也就是移动，
food or nutrition or that acquisition, digestion, excretion, and reproduction,
食物或营养的获取、 消化、排泄和繁殖，
basic functions of life - these are present,
这些生命的基本功能—— 是存在的，
or started growing as evolution progressed.
或者说是随着进化而发展的。
We do not know why that happened — whether it was Darwinism, evolutionary pressures,
我们不知道为什么会这样—— 无论是达尔文主义、进化压力，
natural selection, descent through modification, everything that Darwin wrote
自然选择、变异遗传， 所有达尔文所写
and has since been discussed and debated — all of that somehow came together.
以及此后被讨论和辩论的一切—— 所有这些以某种方式汇集在了一起。
But the nervous system started evolving.
但神经系统开始进化了。
It started becoming more and more sophisticated in terms of being able to respond
它在应对 环境变化方面
to changes in the environment.
变得越来越复杂。
If you are a small fish, all you are worried about is not being gobbled up
如果你是一条小鱼， 你唯一担心的就是不被
by a bigger fish. If you are a bigger fish,
更大的鱼吃掉。 如果你是一条大鱼，
all you are worried about is not being gobbled up by an even bigger fish.
你唯一担心的就是不被 更大的鱼吃掉。
Therefore, imagine being a fish in an aquatic environment:
因此， 想象一下作为一条鱼在水生环境中：
you need sensory organs, you need to detect movement.
你需要感觉器官， 你需要探测运动，
We must be able to perceive sound and other waves
你需要听到一些东西—— 不是以声波的形式，因为声波
so gradually we need eyes
在水中不易传播—— 然后，渐渐地，你需要眼睛
or what we call visual organs to be able to see if a larger organism
或者我们所谓的视觉器官， 以便能看到是否有更大的生物
is moving towards you.
向你移动。
It is hypothesized that, somehow, these evolutionary pressures,
据推测，这些进化压力， 这些生存需求，
these survival needs, started creating and putting pressure in a way
以某种方式开始创造 并施加压力，
that what we call today 'the nervous system' started evolving.
使得我们今天所说的“神经系统” 开始进化。
Fast forward a few billion years, and what we now find in the human brain
快进几十亿年， 我们现在在人脑中发现的
is a highly evolved system which has two basic strata.
是一个高度进化的系统， 它有两个基本层次。
The first strata is in the paleocortex—the old brain —
第一个层次是 古皮层——旧脑——
which takes care of the vegetative functions,
它负责植物性功能，
the fear or the fight response,
恐惧或战斗反应，
the basic kind of response; and above that
这类基本反应； 而在其之上
is what we are going to be talking about the most, probably,
是我们可能将要谈论最多的话题，
which is the cerebral cortex.
那就是大脑皮层。
It is the cerebral cortex which is the most magnificent
大脑皮层是最宏伟的
creation of evolution
进化产物，
from a neurological perspective, and that is critical to know,
从神经学的角度来看， 了解这一点至关重要，
and, hopefully, that allows us, as we move forward in our discussion today,
希望这能让我们 在今天的讨论中继续前进，
as the basis of where we go.
作为我们前进的基础。
I would like to ask, doctor, that in the Bhagavad Gita
我想问博士， 在《薄伽梵歌》中，
there is a striking metaphor of a tree growing upside down with the roots in the brain.
有一个引人注目的比喻，说一棵树 倒着生长，根在脑中。
Now, could you delve into the depths of this metaphor
您能否从神经科学的视角 深入探讨
through the lens of neuroscience,
这个比喻的深层含义，
illuminating its profound implications for our understanding of the mind?
阐明它对我们理解心智的 深远启示？
The Lord Shri Krishna, in the Bhagavad Gita, in the fifteenth chapter,
主克里希纳在《薄伽梵歌》 第十五章中，
describes a tree which is upside down,
描述了一棵倒生之树，
and the stanza that describes it says there exists a tree with its roots in the brain,
描述它的诗节说， 存在一棵树，其根在脑，
and its branches that grow downward, and its leaves are like the Vedas,
其枝干向下生长， 其叶如《吠陀经》，
and the one who knows or has knowledge of this tree
而知晓或拥有此树知识之人，
is a master of the Vedas.
即是《吠陀经》的大师。
Now, the Vedas, as you know, are considered probably the most ancient scriptures
如您所知，《吠陀经》被认为是 或许最古老的经文，
that delve into philosophy but, most importantly, spirituality.
它不仅探讨哲学， 更重要的是，探讨灵性。
So, what does this mean? How does this apply?
那么，这是什么意思呢？ 这如何适用呢？
Probably a more succinct explanation of the nervous system does not exist
或许没有比这更简洁的 对神经系统的解释了，
in as few words as has been described in the Bhagavad Gita.
用如此少的言语， 就像《薄伽梵歌》中所描述的那样。
How does this correlate?
这如何关联起来呢？
The brain, which exists up here, is called the central nervous system,
存在于此的大脑， 被称为中枢神经系统，
the brain and the spinal cord.
包括大脑和脊髓。
It is made up of literally billions and billions
它由数以十亿计的 功能单位构成，
of its functional unit,
它的功能单位，
its basic functional unit called the neurons.
其基本功能单位称为神经元。
The neurons have a cell body,
神经元有一个细胞体，
and they have a long tail which is called an axon,
还有一个长长的尾巴， 叫做轴突，
and these axons, they come down and they pass through,
这些轴突向下延伸， 穿过并构成
constituting our spinal cord as well;
我们的脊髓；
then they come out
然后它们伸出，
of the vertebral column as well as from parts of the brain,
从脊柱以及 大脑的某些部分伸出，
called the cranial nerves or the spinal nerves,
被称为脑神经或脊神经，
and they innervate the entire human body.
它们遍布整个人体。
So, literally, if you think about it in metaphorical terms, you have a tree;
所以，毫不夸张地说，如果用比喻的方式 来思考，你有一棵树；
the animation will make this very clear.
动画会让这一点非常清楚。
The tree which has its roots in the brain, the branches as they get out,
这棵树的根在脑中， 枝干向外延伸，
and they circulate and they are spread across the body,
它们循环并遍布全身，
and they innervate even the smallest sort
甚至支配着我们指尖 最微小的部分
of the final tips of our fingers and every part of our body,
以及身体的每一个部位，
and that is what is referred to by Shri Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita as the leaves;
这就是克里希纳在《薄伽梵歌》中 所指的“树叶”；
and why it is important for us to understand,
而为什么对我们来说 理解这一点很重要，
when it is said that the knowledge of this is the knowledge of the Vedas,
当经文说“知晓此树即知晓吠陀”时，
is that because this anatomical infrastructure provides the substrate through which we can gain
是因为这种解剖学上的基础设施 提供了一个基底，通过它我们可以获得
a realization or an understanding of reality that goes beyond the interpretation
一种对实相的领悟或理解， 这种理解超越了
of either our mind or of our conditionings, and that is true knowledge; it is true 'Vida.'
我们心智或我们制约的解读， 而那才是真正的知识，是真正的“Vida”。
'Vida' means knowledge, as the founder of Sahaja has always said,
正如霎哈嘉的创始人一直所说， “Vida”的意思是知识，
and the knowledge of this tree is only gained through self-awareness.
而对这棵树的知识 只有通过自我觉醒才能获得。
That energy that is present within us, when that energy is awakened,
我们内在存在的那股能量， 当那股能量被唤醒时，
we realize the true nature of this tree, its branches, that is, the nerves,
我们才认识到这棵树的真正本质、 它的枝干，也就是神经，
and the so-called leaves.
以及所谓的“树叶”。
So, as the founder of Sahaja, Shri Mataji, has expressed,
所以，正如霎哈嘉的创始人 锡吕·玛塔吉所表达的，
and She said to me also, a number of times, in the privileged conversation that we had,
她也曾多次对我这样说， 在我们荣幸的交谈中，
that Sahaj, essentially, is a function of our nervous system.
霎哈嘉，本质上，是我们 神经系统的一种功能。
Human spirituality is not predicated, is not dependent on our cardiovascular system,
人类的灵性并非建立在， 也并非依赖于我们的心血管系统、
our digestive system, our endocrine system. No.
消化系统或内分泌系统。不是的。
Human spirituality and its experience is a function of our nervous system,
人类的灵性及其体验 是我们神经系统的一种功能，
and that is exactly where Shri Krishna was going when He explained that in that very short stanza
而这正是克里希纳在《薄伽梵歌》 那段非常简短的诗节中
in the Bhagavad Gita.
所要表达的。
This is so interesting, and I am sure so many of us
这太有趣了， 我相信我们中的很多人
have not had a chance to get to that kind
都没有机会接触到那种解读，
of interpretation, and thanks so much for explaining that to us.
非常感谢您为我们解释这一切。
Could you shed light on the intriguing connections between our physical nervous system
您能阐明我们物理的神经系统 与抽象的
and the abstract notion of a spiritual subtle system,
灵性精微系统概念之间 有趣的联系吗？
and how might our neural processes
我们的神经过程
relate to a deeper spiritual experience?
又可能如何与更深层的灵性体验相关联？
So, let's start off with the gross anatomy and the physiology of the nervous system,
那么，让我们从神经系统的宏观解剖学 和生理学开始，
a quick primer, and then we will move towards the subtler aspect of it
做一个快速的入门介绍，然后我们将转向 它更精微的方面，
and how they correlate.
以及它们是如何关联的。
So, as we discussed in the previous question, the human nervous system comprises
正如我们在前一个问题中讨论的， 人类的神经系统包括
the central nervous system, that's the brain, the spinal cord and then you have
中枢神经系统，也就是大脑、 脊髓，然后还有
the peripheral nervous system as well, which are these nerves,
周围神经系统，也就是这些神经，
and a part of that is the autonomic nervous system.
其中一部分是自主神经系统。
So, a lot of what we will discuss moving forward, and in the subsequent episodes,
所以，我们接下来要讨论的很多内容， 以及在后续的节目中，
will relate to this critical function, which is the autonomic nervous system.
都将与这个关键功能有关， 也就是自主神经系统。
So, let's take a moment to sort of understand what is what.
所以，让我们花点时间来理解 它们各自是什么。
The brain and the spinal cord, which is the central nervous system,
大脑和脊髓，即中枢神经系统，
relates to both, as we discussed earlier,
如我们之前讨论的，既与
vegetative functions as well as our volitional functions:
植物性功能有关，也与我们 的意志功能有关：
thinking, creativity, planning, etc.
思考、创造力、规划等等。
All are functions of this beautiful thing we call the cerebral cortex.
所有这些都是我们称之为 大脑皮层的这个美丽事物的功能。
Besides that, we have locomotion, that is, movement, and I am sitting here right now,
除此之外，我们还有运动功能， 也就是移动，我现在坐在这里，
I know where my joints are, I know where my legs are,
我知道我的关节在哪里， 我知道我的腿在哪里，
my eyes are looking and perceiving reality as we see around us.
我的眼睛正在看着并感知 我们周围的现实。
A critical part of understanding this, and I am going to take a couple of minutes
理解这一点的一个关键部分， 我将花几分钟时间
to explain this because this is important.
来解释，因为这很重要。
Reality, as a human being perceives it— and this is absolutely fascinating—
人类所感知的现实—— 这绝对是令人着迷的——
reality, as every human perceives it,
每个人所感知的实相，
is an interpretation of the brain.
都是大脑的一种诠释。
It takes a while for this to sink in, because the brain itself is completely covered
要消化这一点需要一些时间， 因为大脑本身完全被
within the cranium. It does not interact with the outside world.
颅骨所覆盖。 它不与外界互动。
The eyes receive impulses through the environment.
眼睛通过环境接收脉冲。
The ears get sound waves, and they create impulses— again, electrical impulses.
耳朵接收声波，并产生脉冲—— 同样是电脉冲。
Both from the eyes and the ears, as well as from the environment around,
来自眼睛和耳朵的信号， 以及来自周围环境的信号，
sensory receptors that exist within the skin and the rest of the body
都通过皮肤和身体其他部位的 感觉接收器
are all brought up into the brain, and it is the brain that interprets those signals.
被传送到大脑， 而正是大脑在解读这些信号。
For example, I am looking at a camera as this is being recorded.
例如，我现在正看着一个摄像头， 因为这正在被录制。
My eyes are seeing it, I am hearing myself, I am speaking in the English language.
我的眼睛在看它，我听到我自己的声音， 我在用英语说话。
There are literally millions of processes that are going on in this place right now.
此时此地，正有数以百万计的 过程正在进行。
Because I was born in an era and grew up in an era
因为我出生并成长 在一个时代，
where I know that this machine that I am looking at,
我知道我正在看的 这台机器，
and looking at you,
并看着你，
is called a camera. I know the word for it.
它叫做摄像头。 我知道它的名字。
I know what it does. I know it is a recording device.
我知道它的功能。 我知道它是一个录制设备。
It will record an image. It will record my voice.
它会录制图像。 它会录制我的声音。
But imagine if I came from an era, just a few hundred years ago,
但想象一下，如果我来自 几百年前的时代，
when I did not know what a camera was.
那时我不知道什么是摄像头。
My eyes would still be able to see it, but not recognize it.
我的眼睛仍然能看到它， 但无法认出它。
So, with the same exact object, based on my prior understanding of it,
所以，对于完全相同的物体， 基于我先前的理解，
my reality changes.
我的现实感改变了。
So, it is still a camera.
所以，它仍然是一个摄像头。
It will still do exactly what it is designed to do.
它仍然会完全按照 它的设计来工作。
But because I don't have an understanding of it, my reality of it changes, of how I see it.
但是因为我不理解它， 我对它的现实感，我看待它的方式，就改变了。
I am speaking in English; if somebody doesn't understand English, they will say,
我在说英语；如果有人 不懂英语，他们会说，
"What is he talking about?"
“他在说什么？”
If somebody speaks in a language that I don't understand
如果有人用一种 我不懂的语言说话，
and says the exact same things I am saying,
说的和我现在说的一模一样，
I don't understand it because I don't have knowledge
我听不懂，因为我没有关于
of the language that that person is speaking in.
那个人所说语言的知识。
And this is very important. This is very, very important to understand
这一点非常重要。 在进入灵性话题之前，
before we get into spirituality.
理解这一点至关重要。
Because reality, again, is what we perceive it to be.
因为现实，再次强调， 是我们感知它的样子。
And there is a ton of literature about spirituality that says that the world we see around us
有大量的关于灵性的文献 都说我们周围看到的世界
is really an illusion.
实际上是一种幻象。
Now, of course, the literalist, and from the scientific point of view,
当然，从字面主义者 和科学的角度来看，
that is nonsense. Black is black, white is white,
这简直是无稽之谈。 黑就是黑，白就是白，
red is red, blue is blue, green is green. Why?
红就是红，蓝就是蓝，绿就是绿。为什么？
Because the eye can perceive the wavelengths of visible light based on the spectrum.
因为眼睛可以根据光谱 感知可见光的波长。
So, whether you know green is green or not, you may not know the word,
所以，不管你是否知道绿色是绿色， 你可能不知道这个词，
but ten people, unless they have visual impairment, are going to see green as green and red as red.
但十个人，除非他们有视力障碍， 都会把绿色看成绿色，红色看成红色。
So, within that framework, reality is the same.
所以，在这个框架内，现实是相同的。
But where it changes, where it starts becoming somewhat different, is when we talk about things
但当它发生变化，开始变得 有些不同时，是在我们谈论一些事情的时候，
just as I gave an example of the camera.
就像我刚才举的摄像头的例子。
All of this is important. Why?
所有这些都很重要。为什么？
Because that just tells us,
因为那恰恰告诉我们，
I took some time to explain it. So, my apologies if this was a bit long-winded.
我花了一些时间来解释。 如果这有点冗长，我表示歉意。
But it is important to realize because reality, as a human being perceives it,
但认识到这一点很重要， 因为人类所感知的现实，
depends on his or her prior conditionings
取决于他或她先前的制约
and their understanding and their background knowledge.
以及他们的理解和 背景知识。
If I were to be shown a picture that hangs in the Louvre
如果给我看一张 挂在卢浮宫的画，
of a lady with a very mysterious smile,
画中是一位带着神秘微笑的女士，
considered to be the most famous painting in the world,
被认为是世界上最著名的画作，
perhaps I would recognize it as the Mona Lisa.
或许我会认出那是《蒙娜丽莎》。
But imagine somebody who has never heard of Mona Lisa,
但想象一下，一个从未听说过蒙娜丽莎的人，
who has never heard of Da Vinci,
从未听说过达芬奇，
sees that painting and may not recognize it, because he or she might appreciate the beauty.
看到那幅画，可能认不出来， 因为他或她可能会欣赏其美感。
This is not to take away from the aesthetic sense of the individual,
这并不是要否定个人的审美感，
but he may not recognize it as the Mona Lisa, the perhaps most famous painting in the world.
但他可能不会认出那是《蒙娜丽莎》， 这幅或许是世界上最著名的画作。
All of this is important. Why? Because the world we inhabit,
所有这些都很重要。为什么？ 因为我们所居住的世界，
from the time we are born to the time we die, depends on how our brain has been programmed.
从我们出生到我们死亡， 都取决于我们的大脑是如何被编程的。
Now, let's move to the essence of your question.
现在，让我们回到你问题的核心。
Spirituality is not dependent on, or seeks to elevate an individual above, their conditionings,
灵性并不依赖于，或者说， 它旨在将个体提升到超越其制约的层面，
above their state of knowledge, above whatever their educational status
超越其知识状态，超越其教育状况
may have taught them or not.
可能教给他们或没有教给他们的东西。
Whatever their socio-economic conditionings may have brought upon them.
无论他们的社会经济条件 给他们带来了什么。
Whatever their cultural upbringing may have induced upon them.
无论他们的文化教养 对他们产生了什么影响。
We are all products of our culture, our societies, our beliefs, our educational status,
我们都是我们文化、社会、 信仰、教育水平、
our economic status. Spiritual reality is completely above it all.
经济地位的产物。 而灵性的现实完全超越了这一切。
So, to come back to that example,
所以，回到那个例子，
why is spirituality different,
为什么灵性是不同的，
or how is it correlated?
或者说它是如何关联的？
There exists within us a subtle system that is very different and is universal.
我们内在存在一个精微的系统， 它非常不同，而且是普世的。
Just as the human brain and the spinal cord
就像人脑和脊髓，
and the nerves and the peripheral nervous system is universal,
以及神经和周围神经系统 是普世的一样，
the subtle system, so-called, which is the spiritual system,
这个所谓的精微系统， 也就是灵性系统，
is very different,
是非常不同的，
and it has some anatomical correlates with the gross nervous system.
它与宏观的神经系统 在解剖学上有一些关联。
So, like we have the autonomic nervous system, which has a sympathetic component
所以，就像我们有自主神经系统， 它有交感神经部分
and a parasympathetic component, likewise, we have within us a subtle system
和副交感神经部分一样， 同样，我们内在也有一个精微系统，
that has the so-called energy channels, energy centers, and a way in which a human being,
它有所谓的能量通道、 能量中心，以及一种方式，让人类，
any human being on the planet, can experience reality
地球上的任何一个人， 都可以体验到现实，
completely agnostic of their cultural, philosophical,
而这完全与他们的文化、哲学、
spiritual, educational, linguistic background.
灵性、教育、语言背景无关。
It is definitely interesting to understand how spirituality expands an individual
理解灵性如何以 您所解释的不同方式
in different ways that you have explained, and I am sure, along the course of this series,
拓展个体，这确实很有趣， 而且我确信，在本系列的课程中，
we will get to hear more from you
我们将从您那里听到更多
about that subtle system that you were talking about.
关于您刚才谈到的那个精微系统。
If you could paint us a picture of the human nervous system,
您能否为我们描绘一幅 人类神经系统的图景，
revealing its intricate functions and the fascinating structure,
揭示其错综复杂的功能 和迷人的结构，
and as we zoom out, how does the autonomic nervous system
当我们从宏观角度看，自主神经系统 如何融入
fit into this grand neural tapestry,
这宏大的神经网络之中，
orchestrating our bodies' responses beyond conscious control?
在我们的意识控制之外 协调我们身体的反应？
So, the autonomic nervous system, so-called autonomic,
所以，自主神经系统， 所谓的“自主”，
has its own volitional system.
有它自己的意志系统。
How does this happen?
这是如何发生的呢？
If I start exercising, my heart rate will go up.
如果我开始锻炼， 我的心率会上升。
Why? Because my muscles will need more oxygen; oxygen is carried by blood;
为什么？因为我的肌肉需要更多氧气； 氧气由血液携带；
blood needs to be pumped out at a much faster pace and much greater force.
血液需要以更快的速度 和更大的力量被泵出。
So, the adrenaline will start being pumped out,
所以，肾上腺素 会开始分泌，
and it will constrict my blood vessels, and it will also increase the contractile force
它会收缩我的血管， 同时也会增加我心脏的
of my heart, which will increase the pressure within the system,
收缩力，从而增加 系统内的压力，
and voila, I get more oxygen because I get more blood.
然后，瞧，我就得到了更多氧气， 因为我得到了更多血液。
Likewise breathing, likewise digestion; we don't control these processes.
同样地，呼吸、消化也是如此； 我们无法控制这些过程。
When I eat something, I don't have to tell my stomach
当我吃东西时，我不需要 告诉我的胃
to go ahead and digest it.
去消化它。
I don't have to tell my intestines to go on moving the food forward.
我不需要告诉我的肠道 继续向前推送食物。
All of these are beyond our conscious control. We don't have to think about it.
所有这些都超出了我们的意识控制。 我们不需要去想它。
That is the autonomic nervous system.
那就是自主神经系统。
The autonomic nervous system arises from two parts in the human body.
自主神经系统源自 人体的两个部分。
The first is in the brain, and the other one,
第一部分在大脑， 而另一部分，
is in the sacrum, which is at the bottom
在骶骨，也就是脊柱的底部，
of the vertebral column, as you can see in the animation.
正如你在动画中看到的那样。
It is called the craniosacral outflow.
这被称为颅骶神经传出。
The sympathetic nervous system, which complements
交感神经系统， 它与
the autonomic nervous system,
自主神经系统相辅相成，
also originates in the brain.
也起源于大脑。
Remember the original thing that Shri Krishna spoke about,
记住克里希纳最初谈到的那件事，
or that's in the Bhagavad Gita.
或者说在《薄伽梵歌》中的内容。
That also starts from the brain, and it also emerges from the spinal cord.
它也始于大脑， 并从脊髓中伸出。
So, the autonomic nervous system has two components:
所以，自主神经系统 有两个组成部分：
the parasympathetic and the sympathetic.
副交感神经和交感神经。
These two systems function complementary to each other.
这两个系统相互补充地运作。
They do not antagonize each other,
它们不相互拮抗，
but they complement each other.
而是相互补充。
For example, the sympathetic nervous system will increase the heart rate.
例如，交感神经系统 会提高心率。
It will help in those kinds of actions.
它会帮助进行这类活动。
The parasympathetic, on the other hand, will slow down the heart rate,
而副交感神经则相反， 它会减慢心率，
and it will increase, for example, the flow of the peristalsis, or promote peristalsis,
并且会增加，例如，蠕动的 流动，或者促进蠕动，
which is the movement of food in the gastrointestinal tract.
也就是食物在胃肠道中的移动。
So, the parasympathetic and the sympathetic
所以，副交感神经和交感神经
nervous systems function as complements to each other.
系统作为互补的部分共同运作。
How does it all work? In the brain, as we said, we have these
这一切是如何运作的呢？ 在大脑中，如我们所说，我们有这些
very small nerve bodies called neurons.
非常小的神经体，称为神经元。
The nerves start from there, through the axons.
神经从那里开始，通过轴突。
They come out of the brain in the form of cranial nerves,
它们以脑神经的形式离开大脑，
and then they also come out from the spinal cord.
然后也从脊髓中出来。
These nerves branch out,
这些神经分支出去，
literally branch out,
字面上地分支出去，
and they enter the various organs, the entire organ system.
并进入各种器官，整个器官系统。
So, our eyes, our ears, our lungs, our heart,
所以，我们的眼睛、我们的 耳朵、我们的肺、我们的心脏、
stomach, duodenum, pancreas, you name it,
胃、十二指肠、胰腺，应有尽有，
the reproductive organs, kidneys. All of them are innervated.
生殖器官、肾脏。 所有这些都受到神经支配。
Think of a tree with its branches going out,
想象一棵树，它的枝干伸展开来，
and these tiny, tiny, tiny, tiny, tiny thread-like structures.
还有这些极其微小的、线状的结构。
The expression in medicine is innervation.
在医学上的表达是“神经支配”。
They penetrate into these organs.
它们渗透到这些器官中。
And that is how the autonomic nervous system controls these functions:
自主神经系统就是这样 控制这些功能的：
the heart rate, respiration, gastrointestinal system,
心率、呼吸、胃肠系统、
our endocrine system, by these nerves that are penetrated.
我们的内分泌系统，都是通过这些 渗透进去的神经来控制的。
So, that is your hardware. If you think in terms of hardware and software,
所以，那就是你的硬件。 如果你用硬件和软件的术语来思考，
that is the anatomical hardware.
那就是解剖学上的硬件。
These nerves that penetrate these organs,
这些渗透到器官中的神经，
and based on whether they are parasympathetic nerves
根据它们是副交感神经
or whether they are sympathetic nerves, have different neurotransmitters,
还是交感神经， 会有不同的神经递质，
chemicals that drive the function
这些化学物质驱动着 这些器官的功能。
of those organs.
那些器官的。
So, that in essence is your autonomic nervous system.
所以，这本质上就是你的 自主神经系统。
The word is important because, again, it is outside of volitional control,
这个词很重要，因为再次强调， 它超出了意志的控制，
and that is a good thing because otherwise, it would be impossible to survive
这是件好事，因为否则的话， 要在一分一秒的基础上生存
on a minute-to-minute basis.
是不可能的。
Now, a couple of quick points.
现在，讲几个要点。
What is the main function of the autonomic nervous system?
自主神经系统的 主要功能是什么？
The autonomic nervous system's primary function is to maintain milieu intérieur.
自主神经系统的主要功能 是维持“内部环境”（milieu intérieur）。
It is a kind of a French expression. What does that mean?
这是一个法语表达。 它是什么意思呢？
It ensures that the internal environment in which the organism exists
它确保生物体赖以生存的 内部环境
is maintained in a state of balance.
保持在一种平衡状态。
That word is critical; that function is vital.
这个词至关重要；这个功能至关重要。
So, if I exercise, to go back to the original example,
所以，如果我锻炼，回到 最初的例子，
my heart rate can go up,
我的心率会上升，
but at some point, it does need to be brought down.
但在某个时候，它确实需要被降下来。
Because if it just keeps on going and going and going,
因为它如果一直不停地加速，
at one point, my heart will fail.
到某个点，我的心脏就会衰竭。
So, that's why if there is acceleration, there has to be deceleration.
所以，如果有加速， 就必须有减速。
If there is forward movement, that forward movement, at some moment, has to stop,
如果有前进的运动， 那前进的运动，在某个时刻，必须停止，
and it has to slow down.
而且必须减速。
Let's think in terms of, for example, when we eat food and we have peristaltic movement,
让我们从这个角度思考，例如， 当我们吃东西时，我们有蠕动，
so the food goes down, stomach, duodenum, jejunum, ileum, etc.,
所以食物会向下移动， 经过胃、十二指肠、空肠、回肠等，
and then it goes into the large intestine. All of this is maintained in this absolutely,
然后进入大肠。 所有这些都维持在这个绝对的，
impossibly complex but completely integrated system.
看似不可能复杂但又 完全整合的系统中。
The two components of the autonomic nervous system constantly talk to each other.
自主神经系统的两个组成部分 不断地相互沟通。
They don't function in their own cycles, and that's also very important
它们不是在各自的循环中运作， 这一点也非常重要，
from a spiritual point of view.
从灵性的角度来看。
So, maintaining that internal balance and addressing the requirements of the organism,
所以，维持那种内部平衡 并满足生物体的需求，
as things move along, as the environment around that individual changes, is very important.
随着事物的进展，随着个体 周围环境的变化，是非常重要的。
In common parlance, if you do Google searches or you look at YouTube videos,
在通俗的说法中，如果你用谷歌搜索 或者看YouTube视频，
the autonomic nervous system, they say,
他们会说自主神经系统，
it's something that helps you with flight or fight.
是帮助你进行 “逃跑或战斗”的系统。
If I go, if I am walking, if I am walking in a jungle,
如果我走，如果我在丛林里走，
I see a tiger, my brain recognizes this is danger, I need to start running,
我看到一只老虎，我的大脑识别出这是危险， 我需要开始跑，
my heart rate will go up because, immediately, I need to start running, the body knows it,
我的心率会上升，因为，立刻， 我需要开始跑，身体知道这一点，
off I go. That's flight.
我就跑了。那就是逃跑。
But if there is a smaller danger that I can maybe fight it,
但如果有一个较小的危险， 也许我能对抗它，
same thing, flight or fight responses.
同样的事情，逃跑或战斗的反应。
But throughout our evolution, through measures that we really do not understand,
但在我们的整个进化过程中， 通过我们确实不理解的方式，
through mechanisms that are yet to be elucidated, this system developed within organisms,
通过尚未阐明的机制， 这个系统在生物体内发展起来，
and it is present in mammals, but it is most developed in human beings.
它存在于哺乳动物中， 但在人类中发展得最为完善。
And it is very, very, very important to know it because the subtle system that we shall discuss
了解这一点非常非常重要， 因为我们将要讨论的精微系统，
in the next episodes is the microcosm; the subtle system is the microcosm
在接下来的节目中，是微观世界； 精微系统是微观世界，
that reflects the macrocosm that, at a gross level, is the autonomic nervous system.
它反映了宏观世界，在宏观层面上， 也就是自主神经系统。
Thank you so much for this very detailed explanation,
非常感谢您 如此详细的解释，
and this also covers the next question
这也涵盖了我的下一个问题，
that I had for you, which was how do the parasympathetic
就是关于副交感神经 和交感神经分支
and sympathetic branches distinguish from each other,
如何相互区分，
and how they interact with each other
以及它们如何相互作用
to maintain the body's balance and essential functions, etc.
来维持身体的平衡 和基本功能等等。
This brings me to the last question for today, and the question is about the nerves.
这让我想到今天的最后一个问题， 这个问题是关于神经的。
So, nerves are like the body's electrical wiring, or at least so we heard.
所以，神经就像身体的电线， 或者至少我们是这么听说的。
But how exactly do they transmit messages,
但它们究竟是如何传递信息的，
and why are they crucial for our senses and movements?
为什么它们对我们的 感官和运动至关重要？
So, if you could take us into that electrifying world
所以，如果您能带我们 进入那个充满电能的世界
of nerves, and also at the same time,
——神经的世界，同时，
talk to us about how our nervous system, the autonomic nervous system, and the nerves
也跟我们谈谈我们的神经系统、 自主神经系统和神经
intertwine with the concept of the human spiritual subtle system?
如何与人类灵性精微系统 的概念交织在一起？
So, nerves are
所以，神经是
like the electrical wiring.
就像电线一样。
They are cells, and the way they function is through impulse generation and conduction.
它们是细胞，它们的功能方式 是通过脉冲的产生和传导。
Impulse means an electrical impulse.
脉冲指的是电脉冲。
If you think of this, my hand, as a membrane of the cell membrane.
如果你把我的手 想象成细胞膜。
You have sodium and potassium. These are two positively charged ions
你有钠和钾。 这是两种带正电的离子，
that go across the cell membrane, and when they go across the cell membrane —
它们穿过细胞膜， 当它们穿过细胞膜时——
so, potassium going out, sodium coming in —
所以，钾离子流出， 钠离子流入——
they create a change in the electrical charge
它们在表面两侧 造成了电荷的变化。
across the surface. So, nerve impulse or propagation is
所以，神经脉冲或传播就是
the traveling of this impulse along a line.
这个脉冲沿着一条线传播。
Let's say this is the beginning of the nerve, this is the end; the impulse is generated here,
比如说，这是神经的起点， 这是终点；脉冲在这里产生，
and down it goes.
然后向下传播。
So, that's exactly how the electrical charge travels.
这正是电荷传播的方式。
Of course, in an electrical wire, it's different.
当然，在电线里， 情况是不同的。
It's actually an electrical charge,
那实际上是电荷，
which is very different, from a movement of potassium and sodium ions
这与钾离子和钠离子 在细胞膜两侧的
across membranes.
移动是非常不同的。
This somehow creates awareness. We don't know exactly how it creates it,
这以某种方式创造了意识。 我们不确切知道它是如何创造的，
but we are aware, as we are aware. It's a state that is
但我们是有意识的，就像我们此刻有意识一样。 这是一种
different from when we are asleep. So, this state of awareness is important.
与我们睡觉时不同的状态。 所以，这种意识状态很重要。
We don't know exactly how it is created
我们不确切知道它是如何被创造的
within the brain, but that electrical impulse generation
在大脑内部，但那种电脉冲的产生
is what, literally, as we said before when we answered one of the first questions,
正如我们之前回答第一个问题时所说， 从字面上讲，
is what life is about.
就是生命的本质。
The way it functions is that when the electrical impulse arrives at a point,
它的运作方式是， 当电脉冲到达一个点时，
it causes the release of certain chemicals; they are neurotransmitters.
它会引起某些化学物质的释放； 它们是神经递质。
So, they could be acetylcholine, they could be dopamine,
所以，它们可能是乙酰胆碱， 可能是多巴胺，
they could be serotonin in the brain and in the rest of the organs.
可能是大脑中的血清素 以及其他器官中的。
It could also be adrenaline. These are neurotransmitters that then
也可能是肾上腺素。 这些是神经递质，然后
are transferred across synapses.
它们通过突触(synapse)传递。
Synapses are a very, very important part of the nervous system, particularly in the brain.
突触是神经系统中 非常非常重要的一部分，尤其是在大脑中。
So, what is a synapse? Let's take a look at it. That also helps to answer your question.
那么，什么是突触？让我们来看一下。 这也有助于回答你的问题。
The nerve comes up at one end, ends there, and then the other one begins,
神经在一端到达，在那里结束， 然后另一端开始，
and there is a little bit of a gap. It's called the synaptic cleft.
中间有一点间隙。 这被称为突触间隙。
The nerve impulse comes, releases the neurotransmitter,
神经脉冲传来， 释放神经递质，
it activates the other part, and the impulse is propagated.
它激活另一部分， 脉冲就传播下去了。
Synapses are important. Why? Because when we will see,
突触很重要。为什么？ 因为我们将会看到，
when we will take a deeper look at the brain itself,
当我们更深入地 观察大脑本身时，
neurons form connections with each other.
神经元之间会形成连接。
And these connections are critical for the functioning of the brain.
而这些连接对于 大脑的功能至关重要。
And it is hypothesized, because nobody has nearly understood it,
据推测，因为没有人完全理解它，
because we have billions of neurons, billions.
因为我们有数十亿个神经元，数十亿。
Each one of them interlaced and connected with other neurons.
每一个都与其他神经元 交织和连接。
It's a collective; it's a network.
它是一个集体； 它是一个网络。
Because billions times ten becomes trillions, it is said that what makes us human,
因为数十亿乘以十就是数万亿， 据说，让我们成为人类的，
at the end of the day, is our synaptic connectivity.
归根结底， 是我们突触的连接性。
It is the richness of our cortex that makes it so.
是我们大脑皮层的丰富性 造就了这一切。
And that is why these nerves are so important, because,
这就是为什么这些神经如此重要， 因为，
if you think about it in terms of a calculus function,
如果你用微积分函数的 方式来思考，
like an integral.
就像一个积分。
It's an integral function of all of these trillions of synapses, all firing together,
它是所有这些数万亿个 突触的积分函数，它们一起放电，
this network that exists within us, that constitutes consciousness.
这个存在于我们体内的网络， 构成了意识。
That's the hypothesis. And it is what essentially distinguishes us
这是目前的假设。 而这本质上也是区分我们
from other species on the planet.
与地球上其他物种的因素。
So, the nerves function as individual components of a vastly complex,
所以，神经作为 一个极其复杂、
interlaced, integrated network that ultimately not only creates life,
交织、整合的网络中的 单个组件运作，
but makes us human.
最终不仅创造了生命， 也让我们成为人类。
This is really interesting, and this is very useful information, Dr. Ashish.
这真的很有趣，也非常有用， 阿希什博士。
I can't thank you enough for this very insightful discussion today.
我无法用言语感谢您 今天这场富有洞见的讨论。
We hope to connect with you in our next episode
我们希望在下一期节目中 与您再次联系，
on yet another topic for a deeper understanding
就另一个话题进行更深入的探讨，
of our audiences.
以帮助我们的观众理解。
And we would now like to take our audience to experience the state of meditation
现在，我们想带领我们的观众 去体验冥想的状态，
with a video from the founder of this meditation.
通过一段来自这种冥想创始人的视频。
And it will be easy for you to follow along.
您会很容易跟着做。
We wish you all the very best on this meditative journey.
我们祝愿您在这段冥想旅程中 一切顺利。
Thank you so much. Thank you, Dr. Ashish.
非常感谢。 谢谢您，阿希什博士。
Thank you, Monikaji.
谢谢你，莫妮卡吉。
Shri Mataji: Not much is written, except that we can say it is written, "I will appear before you
锡吕·玛塔吉：记载不多，但我们可以说 经文上写着，“我将如火焰之舌般
like tongues of flames." These are the centers, the chakras.
向你们显现。” 这些就是能量中心，即脉轮。
And it is also said that there is a tree of life.
经文中也说，有一棵生命之树。
Like Shri Krishna has described in Gita that the tree of life is upside down.
就像克里希纳在《薄伽梵歌》中描述的， 生命之树是倒着长的。
The roots are in the brain, and the branches go down in all directions.
根在脑中， 而枝干向四面八方垂下。
Keep your eyes closed.
请闭上眼睛。
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
首先，请把你的右手 放在你的心上。
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
左手始终朝向我。
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
现在，你必须在心中 真诚地说，母亲，我就是那个灵(Spirit)吗？
Ask the question three times in your heart.
在心中问这个问题三次。
This is a very fundamental question.
这是一个非常根本的问题。
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
现在把右手移到 你胃部的左侧，
in the upper part.
在上半部分。
Here press it.
在这里按压。
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
现在，这里是你的掌控中心， 你的指引，你的导师原理（Guru Tattva），如他们所说。
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
所以问一个问题， 母亲，我是自己的主人吗？
This is the question to be asked three times.
这个问题要问 三次。
Mother, am I my own master?
母亲，我是自己的主人吗？
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
现在把你的右手向下移到 腹部的下半部分。
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
现在，这里是所有上天的工作 完成的中心，
all the pure work is done.
所有纯粹的工作都在这里完成。
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
所以要问六次， 因为这个中心有六个花瓣，
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
母亲，请赐予我纯粹的知识。
Six times you just ask.
你只要问六次。
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
由于这个请求， 昆达里尼能量开始被唤醒。
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
现在，为了帮助昆达里尼升起， 你必须与她合作。
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
所以请把你的右手 放在左侧，
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
在腹部的上半部分， 按在胃上。
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
现在，在这里你必须 充满信心地说，
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
为了帮助昆达里尼升起， 母亲，我是自己的导师。
This you have to say ten times.
你必须说十次。
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
这是你必须说的十诫，
that Mother, I am my own master.
母亲，我是自己的导师。
Now, ten times with full confidence.
现在，充满信心地说十次。
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
现在请将你的右手 举到你的心上。
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
现在，在这里你必须 再次充满信心地说，
Mother, I am the Spirit.
母亲，我就是那个灵。
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
这是真相，你就是那个灵。
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
但你必须充满信心地说， 母亲，我就是那个灵。
This you have to say twelve times.
你必须说十二次。
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
现在，人必须知道 全能的上帝是爱的海洋。
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
但最重要的是，他是 宽恕的海洋。
So He forgives.
所以他会宽恕。
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
无论你做错了什么，他都会宽恕。
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
所以不要感到内疚， 把你的右手交叉
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
放在左侧，在你的脖子和肩膀 形成的角落里。
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
现在，在这里你必须 再次充满信心地说，
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
十六次，母亲，我没有罪咎。
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
请说出来，母亲，我没有罪咎。
Sixteen times.
十六次。
I am not guilty at all.
我完全没有罪咎。
Please say it.
请说出来。
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
现在把你的手交叉放在你的额头上， 这是一个非常重要的中心。
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
在这里，你必须发自内心地说， 母亲，我原谅每一个人。
Please say it from your heart.
请发自内心地说。
How many times is not the point.
说多少次不是重点。
Mother, I forgive everyone.
母亲，我原谅每一个人。
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
现在，有些人会说 原谅很难。
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
但我们不原谅或我们原谅， 这其实是一个迷思。
We do not do anything in both the cases.
在这两种情况下，我们什么都没做。
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
但如果我们不原谅， 我们就会落入坏人的圈套。
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
所以请发自内心地说， 母亲，我原谅每一个人。
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
现在请把你的手放在后脑勺的额轮处， 也就是头的后侧，
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
让你的头靠在手上， 并稍微向后推。
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
现在，在这里你必须说， 为了让你自己满意，
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
因为你总是感到内疚， 说，哦，神圣的能量，如果我做错了什么，
please forgive me.
请原谅我。
Please forgive me, from your heart.
请原谅我，发自内心地。
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
完全伸直你的手， 把你的手掌中心
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
放在头顶的囟门区域， 也就是你童年时非常软的骨头那里。
Press it hard.
用力按压。
Press hard your scalp.
用力按压你的头皮。
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
现在你必须移动它七次， 同时说一件事，是你必须请求的，
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
母亲，请赐予我们自性觉醒（自觉）， 因为我不能强加于你。
So you have to ask for it.
所以你必须请求它。
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
用力按压并移动七次， 非常用力地。
Slowly saying that.
慢慢地说出那句话。